We're going to get a little more in
depth and we're going to simplify this
for loop just a little bit. So in order
to do that, we need to talk about this
operator right here. So what I've said
is start at one, go up two and include
10 and go up each time by one. So
because we write this so often, there's
actually some shortcuts you can take
here. So we could say counter instead of
saying counter equals counter + 1. You
may remember from the compound
assignment video that you can say
counter plus equals 1.
So that is one syntax and we could save
this and go over uh sorry to our running
code and it says 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10.
So what you can see is
the alert has run 10 times. Um so this
line of code we only had to write it
once but it ran 10 times and it actually
adjusted because the counter variable
was always adjusting. So each time the
loop went through the counter variable
was now something different. Um,
and because we typically write loops to
go one at a time, we've actually written
some much more um, simple syntax. So
rather than saying counter plus equals
1, we can actually reduce this down to
counter plus. This does the exact same
thing. It says take what's in counter,
go up by one. So if you do counter plus,
it will go up by one every single time.
So, let's save that and go live. And
one, two.
Sorry. Just get through this as fast as
we can. 7 8 9 and 10. Perfect. So, now
we've got a loop that runs um from 1 to
10 and it alerts it. Well, let's say we
want to alert our name right after it.
Um, so I'll just write to. So, we'll
save that and we'll come over and it
just says one, two. Wait a minute, my
name isn't showing up every time.
So, if only there was a way to tell the
for Oh, there's my name.
Interesting. So, it looks like for a for
loop, it only does the line right after
it. So, there is a way that you can get
around this, and this is by using a
block of code. The way you signify a
block of code is you use curly braces.
So an opening curly brace and a closing
curly brace. This says the next line of
code is all grouped together. Everything
between these curly braces is grouped
together. So when the for loop says run
the next line of code every time we go
through the loop, it run it sees these
curly braces and says oh instead of just
running line 13, run everything between
line 13 and line 15. So now if we take
our two lines of code and we put them
inside of those curly braces because
curly braces signify a code block the
for loop knows oh I don't need to run
just one line I need to run everything
in that code block. So, let's save this
and go over. And we get one toa, two
Toa, three toa, and I probably should
have made that Mississippi. So, then I
could be counting one Mississippi, two
Mississippi, but I also didn't want to
try and spell Mississippi live on
screen. All right, so hopefully that
gives you a good idea of how for loops
work and their syntax. You tell it where
you want to start, how long you want to
run, then you tell it how much you want
to change by. In this case, we are just
using the shorthand syntax to say go up
by one every single time. And then in if
you put curly braces you can then put
multiple lines of code and these lines
of code will get run every single time.
Now having done that we can actually
jump into how we could have made your
last project your selection project much
much easier and we will do that in the
next video.